Suspected cholera stool specimens were collected from patients enrolled in the 2% systematic routine surveillance system at the Clinical Research and Service Centre of the International Centre for Diarrheal Disease Research, Bangladesh (ICDDRB). In this surveillance system, every 50th patient attending the hospital is screened for major enteric pathogens. The Dhaka hospital of the ICDDRB identifies cases of cholera throughout the year and treats patients during large outbreaks of the disease. According to the hospital surveillance records, about 88% of the patients report to the ICDDRB Dhaka hospital within <1 day after the first episode of acute diarrhea, while 12% report between 1 and 3 days. For this study, rice water stool samples were collected aseptically from 135 patients who had no prior medication, except that 88% had eaten rice gruel and the remaining 12% had been treated with rice oral rehydration saline (ORS) when they reported to the ICDDRB hospital in Dhaka between March and August 2009. The stool samples for culture (CMs) were immediately placed into Cary Blair medium (sodium thioglycolate, 1.5 g/liter; disodium phosphate, 1.1 g/liter; calcium chloride, 0.1 g/liter; sodium chloride, 5 g/liter; agar, 5 g/liter; pH 8.4) and transported to the laboratory within 30 min. Freshly collected stool samples were used for the dipstick assay, and aliquots were preserved at −20°C in glycerol for subsequent detection of V. cholerae by other methods.